Finding Aid for the James Richardson papers on the Ku Klux Klan in Southern California LSC.1818
UCLA Library Special Collections
James Richardson papers on the Ku Klux Klan in Southern California
1910-1985 (bulk 1975-1985)
1975-1985
UCLA Library Special Collections
Richardson, James
LSC.1818
2.2 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 shoe box)
Research materials, notes, transcripts and audio cassette interviews relating to the Ku Klux Klan group based in Southern California in the late 1970s and early 1980s. These materials were created, collected and assembled by James Richardson (b. 1953), who was a journalist and investigative reporter for The Press-Enterprise (Riverside, Calif.) and other California newspapers. The collection contains Richardson's materials for his investigative reporting on the Ku Klux Klan in Riverside. This includes Richardson's coverage of the 1980 43rd Congressional District election between Republican Clair Burgener and Democrat Tom Metzger, the leader of the Ku Klux Klan in California. The only material in the collection with no connection to the Ku Klux Klan is Richardson's reporting of the conspiracy and perjury trial of San Diego Mayor Roger Hedgecock.
Restrictions on Access
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Richardson, August 8, 2008.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9962910563606533
Biography
The bulk of the collection relates to the Ku Klux Klan group based in the Riverside-San Bernardino area in the late 1970s and early 1980s. These materials were created, collected and assembled by James Richardson (b. 1953), who was a journalist and investigative reporter for The Press-Enterprise (Riverside, Calif.) and other California newspapers.
During this period, the Ku Klux Klan had three branches in California, with the Riverside-San Bernardino group probably being the largest. The Riverside-San Bernardino area "Realm of California" branch was initially part of the national organization "Knights of the Ku Klux Klan," but split from the group in 1979 after disputes between Klan leader Thomas Metzger and Grand Wizard David Duke. Metzger then created the separate organization "Ku Klux Klan of California" (also referred to as the "California Knights of the Ku Klux Klan") and appointed himself State Director.
In 1980, Metzger made headlines when he won the Democratic Party nomination for the U.S. House of Representatives with over 40,000 votes in a San Diego-area district. The Democrats disavowed his candidacy, instead endorsing incumbent four-term Republican Clair Burgener. Metzger lost by over 200,000 votes, which was 86 percent of the vote.
Scope and Content
The collection contains Richardson's notes, transcripts and audio cassettes of interviews, and research materials for his investigative reporting on the Ku Klux Klan in Riverside. This includes Richardson's coverage of the 1980 43rd Congressional District election between Republican incumbent Clair Burgener and Democrat Tom Metzger, the leader of the Ku Klux Klan in California.
The only material in the collection with no connection to the Ku Klux Klan is Richardson's reporting of the conspiracy and perjury trial of San Diego Mayor Roger Hedgecock.
Organization and Arrangement
The original arrangement of the creator was maintained during processing. The only exceptions are for the notebooks and audio cassette tapes which had no discernable order. The notebooks are arranged alphabetically by subject and the cassettes are arranged chronologically.
Ku Klux Klan (1915- )–-California.; Richardson, James -- Archives
- Willis, George, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Richardson, James--article draft, 1980 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Interviews--miscellaneous, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Transcripts and typed notes of interviews with Ku Klux Klan members and public officials.
- New Yorker, 1985 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ku Klux Klan--rallies, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Clippings.
- Ku Klux Klan--publications, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ku Klux Klan--clippings--Southern newspapers, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai B'rith, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Reports and newsletters.
- Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai B'rith, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Clippings of Ku Klux Klan activities.
- Anti-Ku Klux Klan activities, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Press releases, clippings, event announcements.
- Klanwatch Intelligence Report, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Dope ring, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Interviews--Metzger, Tom and Subject "Y", 1979 November, 1980 February (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Ku Klux Klan--leaflets and pamphlets, 1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Metzger, Tom--notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Ku Klux Klan--post-election update, 1981 July-August (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Clippings, California state report, handwritten notes
- Duke, David, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Pamphlets
- Magazine articles, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Ku Klux Klan--handbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 43rd Congressional District election--clippings, 1980 March-November (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ku Klux Klan and National Socialist Party--clippings, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 43rd Congressional District election--campaign trail, 1980 October (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Richardson's notes on Burgener and Metzger.
- Ku Klux Klan--notes, 1980 July 23 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Los Angeles County Commission on Human Relations, 1980 December (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Report
- Richardson, James--book proposal, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Richardson's correspondence and notes to Doubleday editor.
- Metzger, Tom--clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Richardson, James--California Journal article, 1980 September (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Ku Klux Klan--press releases, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Ku Klux Klan--government records, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Motor vehicle registrations and court records involving Ku Klux Klan members.
- Ku Klux Klan--internal grievances, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Johnson, Paul, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Riverside City Council candidate with alleged involvement with Ku Klux Klan.
- Ku Klux Klan--clippings, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Ku Klux Klan--clippings and photographs, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Ku Klux Klan--demonstration, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Notes.
- Ku Klux Klan--Fresno, 1980 January (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Clipping.
- Pepper, George, 1910-1911, 1980-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Handwritten notes, transcript of interview with James Richardson, correspondence with Ku Klux Klan members, photocopy of Encyclopedia Britannica entry for "Negro."
- Howard, Dovard--shooting, 1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Notes, clipping.
- 43rd Congressional District election--election night, 1980 November (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Notes, election returns, clippings, campaign materials.
- Burgener, Clair--campaign materials, 1974, 1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 43rd Congressional District election--primary election, 1980 March-September (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Interviews, notes, clippings relating to primary election and responses to Metzger's victory.
- 43rd Congressional District election--Democratic Party resolutions, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Metzger, Tom--campaign literature, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Metzger, Tom--campaign financial reports, 1980 October-December (Box 3, Folder 10)
- National Minority Advisory Council on Criminal Justice, 1979 October (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Transcript of proceedings at which Tom Metzger spoke.
- Dent, Robert, 1980 October (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Probation officer report for murder conviction of fellow Ku Klux Klan member.
- Ku Klux Klan--Southern California activities, 1977-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Clippings, interviews, notes.
- Ku Klux Klan--photographs, 1980-1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Thompson, Jerry--clippings, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Articles of Tennessean newspaper reporter who went undercover as Ku Klux Klan member.
- Oceanside incident, 1980 March 16 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Clippings, notes.
- Oceanside incident, 1980 March 17-20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Ku Klux Klan--clippings--San Diego newspapers, 1980 October 14-16 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Oceanside incident--wire photographs, 1980 March 15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Hedgecock, Roger--trial, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Conspiracy and perjury trial of San Diego Mayor Roger Hedgecock. Clippings, notes, correspondence. This folder contains the only material in the collection with no connection to the Ku Klux Klan.
- 43rd Congressional District election--opposition and election statistics, 1980 October-November (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Notes, interviews of Metzger's opponents, election results predictions.
- Yellen, Ben--newsletters, 1969, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Water and land issues in the Imperial Valley, California
- Richardson, James--clippings, 1980 April-October (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Articles published in Press-Enterprise.
- Burgener, Clair--notes, 1980 October (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Three notebooks.
- Burgener, Clair--notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Two notebooks.
- Election night--notes, 1980 November 4 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  One notebook.
- Interviews--notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Metzger, Tom--notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Pepper, George--notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Richardson, James--address book, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Interviews--Pepper, George and John Edens--audio cassette, 1979 December 18 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Interviews--Pepper, George and John Edens--audio cassette, 1979 December 18 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Interviews--Ku Klux Klan meeting--audio cassette, 1980 January 20 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Interviews--Fraley, Bernie Lee and George Pepper--audio cassette, 1980 February 8 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Interviews--Metzger, Tom--audio cassette, 1980 February 13 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Parts 1 and 2.
- Interviews--Metzger, Tom--audio cassette, 1980 February 13 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Parts 3 and 4.
- Interviews--Alcorn, Irvin--audio cassette, 1980 February 22 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Interviews--Oceanside incident--audio cassette, 1980 March 15 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Interviews--Pepper, George--audio cassette, 1980 April 25 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Interviews--Johnson, Paul and Clair Burgener--audio cassette, 1980 July 10, 1980 September 26 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Interviews--Anti-Ku Klux Klan march--audio cassette, 1980 October 4 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  Progressive Labor Party and International Committee against Racism.
- Interviews--Solomon, Ben--audio cassette, 1980 October 29 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  NAACP leader.
- Interviews--Burgener, Clair and Tom Metzger--audio cassette, 1980 October 21 and 22 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Interviews--Metzger, Tom--audio cassette, 1980 October 22 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  At El Centro Detention Center
- Interviews--Metzger, Tom and Ben Yellen--audio cassette, 1980 October 22 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  At El Centro Detention Center and Brawley, California.
- Interviews--Metzger, Tom--audio cassette, 1980 October 24 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  San Diego County Democratic Central Committee trial.
- Interviews--Morrow, Floyd--audio cassette, 1980 October 24 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  Chairperson, San Diego County Democratic Central Committee.
- Interviews--Cross burning-audio cassette, 1980 November 1 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  Parts 1 and 2. At George Pepper's house in Fontana.
- Interviews--Cross burning--audio cassette, 1980 November 1 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  Part 3.
- Interviews--Election night--audio cassette, 1980 November 4 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  Tom Metzger, Larry Kapiloff, Connie Lemen, Tim Field
- Interviews--Johnson, P. and NAACP anti-Ku Klux Klan march--audio cassette, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)